THOMAS C. BOTHEN

6333 Tremont Road Willowbrook, Illinois 60527 tcbothen@aol.com 630.887.1657

SUMMARY

Educator and finance professional with demonstrated experience in financial operations, analysis and accounting. Leadership positions in real estate operations, insurance company risk management. Leadership role at the division level in strategic planning and budgeting. Travel internationally providing finance training to real estate professionals. Very effective communicator and coach. M.B.A., University of Chicago Graduate School of Business.

EXPERIENCE

UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS CHICAGO, Chicago, IL Associate Director, Center for Urban Real Estate Director, Graduate Studies; Masters Degree in Real Estate Program

2004 – Present

- Teach real estate finance, market analysis and real estate development at graduate and undergraduate levels. Received four academic commendation letters for excellent teaching
- Organized advisory board of prominent real estate industry professionals to advise on matters of curriculum and current real estate trends to maximize student industry preparedness
- Prepared real estate development course with extensive use of sophisticated modeling tools for financial, market and demographic analysis
- Lead collaborator for development of on-line blended learning delivery of real estate certificate program
- Conducted extensive study of housing markets and pricing post 2008 financial downturn
- Travel and study in Mexico City and Moscow extending to housing and commercial real estate markets
- Recognized for exceptional contributions to MRE program
- Completed applications research projects for Chicago Park District and Center for Business Education and Development
- Co-investigator with College of Urban Planning contributing research for national study to quantify real estate value attributed to rapid transit proximity

STEPHENS COMMERCIAL REALTY. Aurora, IL **Development Officer**

2000-2004

Manage large site land sales, sale of investment properties, master site development planning, state and local incentives. Consult with US Army for asset valuation and redevelopment projects.

- Completed marketing and sale of \$6 million of properties.
- Lead member of delegation to Russian Guild of Realtors for training members in western market analysis and financial concepts.

USAA REALTY COMPANY, Rosemont, IL

1992-2000

Assistant Vice President, Operations and New Business Development

Strategy, operations and development responsibilities for multi-state portfolio of industrial and office properties. Strong logistics and construction experience. Excellent knowledge of technology applications. Operate in EVA environment. Responsible for \$25 million business unit.

- Directed leasing program which generated over \$117 million in revenue and brought portfolio occupancy to
- Sourced and managed development and construction of major industrial and retail projects generating IRR of
- Initiated new contract specifications which reduced annual operating costs by \$218,000.
- Spearheaded aggressive management of real estate tax assessments generating annual savings of \$175,000.
- Designed repair solution and trained engineering staff for project which saved \$560,000
- Instituted technique which reduced 50 page property document to concise two page report saving hundreds of hours of staff time.

 Completed market analysis on commercial land that repositioned property for retail use and generated profit of \$8.26 million.

Thomas C. Bothen Page 2

MCCOLLOM REALTY, Oak Park, IL

1992

Leasing and Management

Performed leasing and property management operations at CBD and suburban office properties and initiated construction management procedures.

- Set up management procedures and operated temporary facility for 8,000 college students displaced by local disaster.
- Implemented construction management procedures to control costs.

BALCOR COMPANY, Skokie, IL

1991-1992

Assistant Vice President

Managed portfolio of 60 properties including office, multi-family and retail. Prepared quarterly investor letters and assisted in preparation of SEC filings. Performed analysis of underwriting and financial position for deal restructuring.

- Recommended implementation of mapping program to track and rank properties according to type and performance.
- Conducted analysis and recommended debt restructuring for properties.

CRS GROUP, Oak Brook, IL Principal

1988-1991

• Performed acquisition due diligence for CBD office properties and consulting engagements for Helene Curtis, Continental Materials and Chicago Title and Trust in areas of taxation and pension plan reporting.

WESTCHESTER SQUARE, Oak Brook, IL Executive Vice President & CFO

1977-1988

• Organized and directed real estate investment and property management firm.

EDUCATION/LICENSES

Risk Management Program, Darden School, University of Virginia

MBA, Finance & Economics, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL

BA, Finance & Accounting, Loyola University, Chicago, IL.

1974

- Real Estate Broker, Illinois
- Senior Instructor, CCIM: travel internationally teaching real estate finance and market analysis courses